{"tossups": [{"question": "Trade in this desert declined after the Battle of Tondibi, relegating merchants to routes such as Azalai and Taoudenni. While traveling from Sijilmasa to the Oualata Oasis, Ibn Battuta wrote of how Berber guides were influential in the trade of this desert. The vital Taghaza salt mines were located in this desert, where dromedaries were domesticated for travel. For ten points, name this large desert that Arab traders crossed to reach West Africa.", "answer": "<b> Sahara</b> Desert", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city was known to the Slavs as Tsargrad. Theodosius II used the help of fans who watched chariot racing in this city\u2019s Hippodrome to build this city\u2019s famous double walls. An engineer named Orban helped build a giant cannon that could fire 600 pound cannonballs; that cannon was used in Mehmed II\u2019s conquest of this city in 1453. For ten points, name this capital of the Byzantine Empire, which was later renamed Istanbul.", "answer": "<b> Constantinople</b> (do not accept Istanbul or Byzantium)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1972, one of these events occurred in the Black Hills and resulted in over 200 deaths. The Stone Fork Fishing and Hunting Club was accused of causing one of these events in 1889 that destroyed Johnstown, Pennsylvania and killed over 2,200 people. President Herbert Hoover dealt with one of these events that made hundreds of thousands of people homeless in 1927. For ten points, name this type of natural disaster that frequently occurs along the Mississippi River.", "answer": "<b> flood</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This painting\u2019s date and the artist\u2019s name are depicted on a handkerchief held by a boy. Two figures on either side of this painting\u2019s title figure are depicted in golden robes. This painting is noted for its distinct \u201cheaven\u201d and \u201cearth\u201d sections, the latter of which depicts Saint Stephen and Saint Augustine descending for the title event. For ten points, name this El Greco painting showing the interment of the title nobleman.", "answer": "The<b> Burial of the Count of Orgaz</b> (accept El<b> Entierro del Senor de Orgaz</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A general from this country escaped a purge of high-ranking officers by climbing a wall into an Iraqi embassy. One leader of this country promoted the Nasikom ideology and the five principles, or pancasila, and was overthrown in 1967 before a massive purge of Communists. For ten points, name this Asian archipelagic country that was led during the Cold War by Sukarno and Suharto.", "answer": "<b> Indonesia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This company\u2019s logo was inspired by a tattoo of a star its founder received while serving on the<em> Emily</em> <em>Morgan</em>. A victim of the<em> Titanic</em> sinking, Isidor Strauss, bought this company in 1895. This company\u2019s first location in New York made over $300 on its first day in 1858 and expanded after employing illuminated shopping displays. The flagship store of this brand is in Herald Square in Manhattan. For ten points, name this national department store chain that sponsors an annual Thanksgiving Day parade in New York.", "answer": "R.H.<b> Macy</b> and Co. (accept<b> Macy</b>\u2019s Inc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This conflict featured an Italian naval intervention that was thwarted at Lissa in the first sea battle between ironclad fleets. Albrecht von Roon opened the draft to all male citizens prior to this conflict, which broke out after one side violated the Gastein Convention. This conflict was decided at the battle of Sadowa, which allowed the winners to take control of Schleswig and Holstein. For ten points, name this 1866 war in which Prussia defeated Austria within two months.", "answer": "<b> Seven Weeks\u2019</b> War (accept<b> Austro-Prussian</b> War before \u201cPrussia\u201d is read; prompt on it afterward; prompt on Unification War; prompt on German (Civil) War)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In Vedic Hinduism, this substance is the center of the<em> yajna</em> ritual. Zoroastrians protect this substance, called<em> atar</em>, in temples named for it. In 1861, Queen Victoria banned the practice of<em> sati</em>, whereby Hindu widows would kill themselves with this substance. This substance is personified by the Hindu god Agni. For ten points, name this substance which, in Greek myth, Prometheus stole from the gods and gave to humans.", "answer": "<b> fire</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This type of military maneuver was introduced to Japan by Takeda Shinjin and was defeated by Oda Nobunaga with the use of firearms at the first \u201cmodern\u201d Japanese battle, the Battle of Nagashino. Gustavus Adolphus was killed at Lubeck while leading one of these maneuvers. These maneuvers were the hammer in the Macedonian \u201chammer and anvil\u201d strategy, and they were used as opening maneuvers in battles for centuries until infantry squares rendered them obsolete. For ten points, name this military maneuver that involves a full speed ride at an enemy force.", "answer": "<b> cavalry charge</b> (accept clear knowledge equivalents; prompt on partial answers, like \u201ccavalry maneuvers,\u201d \u201ccharges,\u201d etc.)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man and his aides were targeted in a failed assassination attempt by Ulric Dahlgren. This man was captured near Irwinville, legendarily while dressed in the clothing of his wife, Varina. This man served as Secretary of War under Franklin Pierce; later, in a more famous role alongside Alexander Stephens, he issued General Order 14 allowing slaves into the army and appointed Robert E. Lee commander of the Army of Northern Virginia. For ten points, name this only President of the Confederate States of America.", "answer": "Jefferson<b> Davis</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This city signed the Pactum Warmundi with Jerusalem. Marco Polo was allegedly captured following this city\u2019s defeat at Curzola, and this city was victorious in the War of Chioggia. The League of Cambrai opposed this city that was once led by Enrico Dandolo, the man who enticed the Fourth Crusade to attack Constantinople. This enemy of Genoa elected leaders known as doges. For ten points, name this Italian city that dominated the Adriatic Sea and is built around a series of canals.", "answer": "Most Serene Republic of<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The perpetrator of this crime took advantage of a hot day to bring a handkerchief without suspicion. An X-ray machine constructed by Thomas Edison was sent to doctors in the aftermath of this crime, whose perpetrator was inspired by the killing of Umberto I of Italy. While reaching in for a handshake at the Pan-American Exposition, a gun was produced by Leon Czolgosz [chol-gosh]. For ten points, name this 1901 assassination that paved the way for Theodore Roosevelt to become president.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> shooting</b>, etc.) of William<b> McKinley</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this event, a fact-finding mission was dispatched on a world tour that recommended basing its country\u2019s army and parliament on Prussia\u2019s. This event was</b> <b>preceded by a war during which the Republic of Ezo was declared, the (+)</b> <b>Boshin War.</b> <b>This event provoked a rebellion among disenfranchised warriors in Satsuma province, and the Charter Oath was issued during this event. This event marked the (*) </b> end of a period that had begun with Tokugawa Ieyasu\u2019s conquest of Japan 250 years earlier. For ten points, name this late 1860s event during which power was given back to Japan\u2019s imperial house.", "answer": "<b> Meiji Restoration</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In the aftermath of this event, Clara Lemlich led the Uprising of the 20,000. Attorney Max Steuer worked to discredit Kate Alterman\u2019s testimony as he defended (+) Max Blanck and Isaac Harris for their role in this event. The Committee on Public Safety to investigate this event was led by future Secretary of (*)</b> Labor Frances Perkins. Over 140 people died in this event, many because emergency exits had been locked. For ten points, name this 1911 event, the deadliest industrial fire in New York City history.", "answer": "<b> Triangle Shirtwaist</b> factory fire", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a city named for this landmark, the Hoover Chemical Company dumped toxic waste that surfaced near the 93rd and 99th street schools. The namesake ship of the</b><em><b> Caroline</b></em><b> affair</b> <b>was destroyed near this landmark. The (+)</b> <b>EPA Superfund was created after a scandal in</b> <b>the Love Canal neighborhood of a city named for this landmark. Annie Taylor became the first person to traverse this landmark in a (*)</b> barrel in 1901. For ten points, name this cascade on the border between Canada and New York.", "answer": "<b> Niagara Falls</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One leader of this country said he admired Hitler because \u201che pulled his country</b> <b>together,\u201d and a first lady of this country promised to \u201cclap hands when I see</b> <b>another monk barbecue.\u201d In this country, (+)</b> <b>Binh Xuyen [bin shu-yen] mafia</b> <b>were responsible for killing a leader whose brother, Nhu, ran the secret police. The</b> <b>Strategic (*)</b> Hamlet Program tried to relocate this country\u2019s rural population. For ten points, name this country that was led by Ngo Dinh Diem [no din diem] and fought the Communists from its northern neighbor with American assistance.", "answer": "<b> South Vietnam</b> (accept<b> Republic of Vietnam</b>,<b> RVN</b>; prompt on Vietnam alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}